Guide to the Woman's Suffrage Realia Collection, 1894-1915 and undated RL.11032
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Woman's suffrage realia collection
1894-1915 and undated.
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
RL.11032
45 items
Collection comprises 43 woman's suffrage movement buttons, pins, pencil, and badges, along with a contemporary hair pins tin used to hold 32 of the items. There are materials from suffrage movements in both the United Kingdom and the United States. Also includes two "Votes for Women" souvenir and program paper napkins for a march and a demonstration in London.
Access Restrictions
Collection is open for research.
Arrangement
Organized according to United Kingdom or United States suffrage movement item.
Collection Overview
Collection comprises 43 woman's suffrage movement buttons, pins, pencil, and badges, along with a contemporary hair pins tin used to hold 32 of the items. There are materials from suffrage movements in both the United Kingdom and the United States. Organizations present include the Woman's Peace Party, Catholic Women's Suffrage Society, Women's Freedom League, National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies, Cymeric Suffrage Union, Men's League for Women's Suffrage, Women's Social and Political Union (W.S.P.U.), and the Woman's Suffrage National Aid Corps, an organization for which there is a badge as well. One pin advocates "Votes for Women, 1915," another, "Votes for Women, Patriotism." Includes a pencil from the Women's Freedom League, which was intended to be worn on a necklace. There are several anti-suffrage buttons and pins from the United States, as well, along with buttons featuring portraits of women suffragists, and a Woman's Christian Temperance Union Liberty Bell pin. Includes a badge to the 37th annual convention of the New York State Woman Suffrage Association, held in Rochester, October 24-27, 1905. Consists of a yellow ribbon with pin at top and a medallion portrait of Susan B. Anthony attached at bottom of ribbon. Also present is a "Votes for Women" enamel flag pin that was worn by supporters in both countries.
Also includes two "Votes for Women" souvenir and program paper napkins for a march and a demonstration in London. The napkins feature decorative borders.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Woman's Suffrage Realia Collection was received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2015 and gift in 2016.
Women -- Suffrage -- United States; Women -- Suffrage -- Great Britain; Women -- Suffrage -- Collectibles; Realia; Buttons (information artifacts); Pins (jewelry); Badges; Napkins (culinary textile); Sallie Bingham Center for Women's History and Culture; Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
- Suffrage buttons, pins, and badges collection, 1894-1915 and undated; 43 items
  - United Kingdom, 1910 and undated; 13 items
    - National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies pins and button, 3 items
      Biographical / Historical
      The National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies (NUWSS) was an organisation of women's suffrage societies in the United Kingdom. The group was founded in 1897 by the merger of the National Central Society for Women's Suffrage and the Central Committee, National Society for Women's Suffrage, the groups having originally split in 1888. The groups united under the leadership of Millicent Fawcett, who was the president of the society for more than twenty years. The organisation was democratic, aiming to achieve women's suffrage through peaceful and legal means, in particular by introducing Parliamentary Bills and holding meetings to explain and promote their aims.
      - "National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies." Publisher statement on back of enamel pin: W. C. Lewis, Howard Street, Birm[ha?]m, 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
        Immediate Source of Acquisition
        Acquired as part of the Lisa Unger Baskin Collection (David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library)
      - "National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies Constitutional Non Party." No publishing information present on back of enamel pin., 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "National Union of Women's Suffrage Societies." On back of button: "Manufactured by the Merchants' Portrait Co., Kentish Town Road, London, N. W.", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
    - Women's Freedom League pin, necklace pencil, button, and badge, 4 items
      The Women's Freedom League was an organisation in the United Kingdom which campaigned for women's suffrage and sexual equality. The group was founded in 1907 by seventy members of the Women's Social and Political Union (WSPU) including Teresa Billington-Greig, Charlotte Despard, Elizabeth How-Martyn, and Margaret Nevinson. They disagreed with Christabel Pankhurst's announcement that the WSPU's annual conference was cancelled and that future decisions would be taken by a committee which she would appoint.
      The League also opposed violence, instead using non-violent forms of protest such as non-payment of taxes, refusing to complete census forms and organising demonstrations, including members chaining themselves to objects in the Houses of Parliament. It grew to over 4,000 members and published The Vote newspaper. They continued their pacifism during World War I, supporting the Women's Peace Council. On the outbreak of war, they suspended their campaigns and undertook voluntary work, but in 1916 they restarted their lobbying activities. They also formed the Women's Suffrage National Aid Corps, to provide for women and children whose financial support had been undermined by the war.
      In the 1918 UK general election, Despard, How-Martyn and Emily Frost Phipps stood unsuccessfully in London constituencies as independent women's rights anti-war candidates. They celebrated the achievement of suffrage and refocussed their activities on equality, including equal pay and equality of morality. The group declined in membership, but was not dissolved until 1961.
      - "Womens Freedom League Votes for Women." No publishing information present on back of enamel pin., 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Women's Freedom League Votes for Women" necklace pencil. No publishing information present., 1 items 9.5 cm (Box 1)
      - "Women's Suffrage National Aid Corps." On back of button: "Manufactured by the Merchants' Portrait Co., Kentish Town Road, London, N. W. ", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Women's Suffrage National Aid Corps." No other information on badge., 1 items 5 x 4 cm (Box 1)
    - Catholic Women's Suffrage Society button, 1 items
      Two young women, Mary Kendall and Gabrielle Jeffrey, met at a Women's Social and Political Union meeting of released suffragette prisoners at Holloway. Together with Beatrice Gadsby, they then founded the Catholic Women's Suffrage Society (CWSS), which, symbolically, held its first meeting on 25 March 1911, on the Feast of the Annunciation. Unlike other church suffrage groups, CWSS leadership was reserved to women, though men were allowed associate membership.
      - "Catholic Women's Suffrage Society." On back of button: "Manufactured by the Merchants' Portrait Co., Kentish Town Road, London, N. W. ", 1 items 3 cm diameter (Box 1)
    - Women's Social and Political Union button, 1 items
      The Women's Social and Political Union (WSPU) was the leading militant organisation campaigning for Women's suffrage in Great Britain, 1903–1917. Its membership and policies were controlled by Emmeline Pankhurst and her daughters Christabel and Sylvia (although Sylvia broke away). It was best known for hunger strikes (and forced feeding), for breaking windows in prominent buildings, and for night-time arson of unoccupied houses and churches.
      - "Votes for Women W. S. P. U." On back of button: "Manufactured by the Merchants' Portrait Co., Kentish Town Road, London, N. W. ", 1 items 3.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
    - Men's League for Women's Suffrage, 1 items
      In 1907, several left-wing intellectuals, including Henry Nevinson, Laurence Housman, Charles Corbett, Henry Brailsford, C. E. M. Joad, Israel Zangwill, Hugh Franklin, Henry Harben, Gerald Gould, Charles Mansell-Moullin, and 32 other men formed the Men's League for Women's Suffrage "with the object of bringing to bear upon the movement the electoral power of men. To obtain for women the vote on the same terms as those on which it is now, or may in the future, be granted to men."
      - "Men's League for Womans Suffrage." No publishing information present on back of button., 1 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
    - Cymric Suffrage Union button, 1 items
      The Cymric Suffrage Union was founded in 1911 by Edith Mansell-Moullin, and united Welsh men and women in putting the enfranchisement of women before any other cause. The organization's handbills and other materials were written or translated into Welsh, and meetings were held in English and Welsh.
      - "Cymric Suffrage Union, Etholfraint I Doynes." No publishing information present on back of button., 1 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
    - General, Pro-Suffrage button and pin, 2 items
      - "Votes for Women." On back of button: Pellett Ltd., 2 High Holborn, London., 1 items 3 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Women's Suffrage" enamel bar pin, about 1910, 1 items (Box 1)
  - United States, 1896-1915 and undated; 19 items
    - Buttons featuring portraits of female suffragists, 2 items
      - Suffragist. On back of button: "Manufactured by St. Louis Button Co., St. Louis, Mo. Pat. Aug. 8 '99", 1 items (Box 1)
      - Two suffragists. On back of button: "The Whitehead & Hoag Co, Newark, N.J., Allied Printing, Trades Council, Union Label, Newark, N.J., Patented July 17,1894; April 14, 1896; July 21, 1896", 1 items (Box 1)
    - Woman's Peace Party pin
      The Woman's Peace Party was an American organization established as a result of a three-day peace meeting organized by Jane Addams and other feminists in response to the beginning of World War I in Europe in 1914. The conference, held in January 1915 in Washington, D.C., brought together women from diverse organizations who unanimously agreed on most issues under discussion, including the call for limitation of arms, mediation of the European conflict, and the removal of the economic causes of war. The peace and suffrage movements were definitively united when a plank calling for the vote for women was successfully added to the party platform.
      - "Peace." On back of enamel pin: "Womans Peace Party, Hyman & Co., Chicago", 1 items (Box 1)
    - Woman's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU) Liberty bell pin
      Woman's Christian Temperance Union (WCTU), American organization, founded in November 1874 in Cleveland, Ohio, in response to the "Woman's Crusade," a series of temperance demonstrations that swept through New York and much of the Midwest in 1873–1874. Annie Wittenmyer, an experienced wartime fund-raiser and administrator, was elected president at the WCTU's founding in 1874. During her five-year tenure the WCTU developed a network of more than 1,000 local affiliates and began publishing a journal. Dissension, however, arose as a segment of the WCTU led by Frances Willard called for the addition of suffrage to the group's platform enjoining abstinence from alcohol. In 1879 Wittenmyer, who opposed such a move, was replaced by Willard. For the next two decades Willard led the temperance movement as the WCTU became one of the largest and most influential women's groups of the 19th century. She expanded the organization's platform to include such issues as labour laws and prison reform, and in 1891 she became president of the World WCTU (founded 1883). The WCTU also campaigned for women's right to vote, though its support posed problems for suffragists as the alcohol industry became a powerful opponent of the movement. With Willard's death in 1898, the WCTU began to distance itself from feminist groups, instead focusing primarily on prohibition. Though its membership steadily declined following the passage of the Eighteenth Amendment (Prohibition) in 1919, the WCTU continued to operate through the 20th century.
      - "WCTU" ribbons with stick pin. On back of brass Liberty Bell: "Woman's Liberty Bell. Justice, Equality, 1915, Pennsylvania. W & H Co., Newark, N.J.", 1 items (Box 1)
    - New York State Woman Suffrage Association 37th annual convention badge
      Scope and Contents
      Badge to the 37th annual convention of the New York State Woman Suffrage Association, held in Rochester, October 24-27, 1905. Consists of a yellow ribbon with pin at top and a medallion portrait of Susan B. Anthony attached at bottom of ribbon. On back of medallion in black text on yellow background: "Perfect Equality of Rights for Women" Susan B. Anthony.
      - Text stitched on ribbon in white thread: N.Y.S.W.S.A. 37th Annual Convention. Rochester Oct. 24-27 1905. On pin back: "Whitehead & Hoag Co., Newark, New Jersey." (Box 3)
    - General, pro-suffrage buttons, 9 items
      - "Votes for Women." No information on back of button., 4 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Votes for Women." No information on back of button. (Box 2)
        2 copies.
        Gift of Kenneth Hubbard, 2016
      - "Votes for Women." On back of button: "Lucke Badge & Button Co., Badges, Buttons, Novelties, Baltimore, Md.", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Votes for Women." On back of button: "National Equipment Co., 12 E. 23rd St., New York, Tel. 2477-Gram.", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Votes for Women, 1915." On back of button: "The Whitehead & Hoag Co., Buttons, Badges, Novelties, and Signs, Newark, NJ.", 1 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Vote Yes Woman Suffrage October 19." On back of pin: "The Sommer Badge Mfg. Co., 71 Liberty St., Newark, NJ.", 1 items 3 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Votes for Women, Patriotism." No information on back of button., 1 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - Votes for Women 1915, with sunrise. On back of button: "The Whitehead & Hoag Co., Buttons, Badges, Novelties, and Signs, Newark, NJ." Written in pen or pencil on back of button: "AME.", 1 items (Box 2)
      - Vote for Woman Suffrage Nov. 6th. No information on back of button., 1 items (Box 2)
      - Penna. Votes for Women 1915. On back of button: "The Whitehead & Hoag Co., Buttons, Badges, Novelties, and Signs, Newark, NJ.", 1 items (Box 2)
      - Against the Repeal of the 19th Amendment. No information on back of button., 1 items (Box 2)
    - General, anti-suffrage buttons, 4 items
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "Phila. Badge Co., 134 N. 8th St., Phila.", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "Bastian Bros.... and Celluloid Novelites, Rochester, N.Y.", 1 items 2.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "Bastian Bros.... and Celluloid Novelites, Rochester, N.Y." (Box 2)
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "N R Man, American Union Label Manufacturer, Lib&B. A., Factory, Milford, N.H.", 1 items 1.5 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "Made by hrman [ilegible] Milford, NH." (Box 2)
      - "Vote No on Woman Suffrage." On back of button: "By hrman Mfg. Co. Boston, Mass." (Box 2)
        Gift of Kenneth Hubbard, 2016.
      - "Anti suffrage." On back of button: "The Whitehead & Hoag Co., Buttons, Badges, Novelties, and Signs, Newark, NJ.", 1 items 2 cm diameter (Box 1)
      - "Repeal the 19th Amendment." No information on back of button. (Box 2)
  - United Kingdom and United States, undated, 1 items
    - "Votes for Women" flag pin. No markings on the back of the enamel pin., 1 items (Box 1)
  - Hair pins tin box with dividers, 1 items (Box 1)
    Tin box for hair pins, with internal dividers, used by collector to store the suffrage buttons, pins, and badges collection.
- Votes for Women souvenir and program paper napkins, 1907 and undated
  - Paper napkins (Folder 1)